<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PRIMENT on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/categories/priment/</link>
    <description>Recent content in PRIMENT on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>`{year}`</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/categories/priment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Something old, something new, something borrowed, something blue</title>
      <link>/post/update2-february/update2-february/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update2-february/update2-february/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The moment for the second edition of the HEART&amp;rsquo;s one-day introductory course to health economics arrived at last! The course, led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=RMHUN48&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rachael Hunter&lt;/a&gt; and called &amp;ldquo;Understanding health economics in clinical trials&amp;rdquo;, took place on Tuesday 11 February and was prepared in collaboration between the HEART group and the Institute of Clinical Trials and Methodology (ICTM). I believe this second edition of the course was a success both in terms of the quality/quantity of the material covered during the six sessions throughout the day, as well as in terms of the positive feedback we received from the participants. Also, this time a new HEART member (&lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=MCCLE13&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Marie&lt;/a&gt;) joined the group and very nicely delivered the session about patient reported outcome measures (PROMs), engaging in nice discussions with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a couple of personal notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I recently attended a very interesting meeting about missing data methodology which was held by an international group of very talented senior and junior statisticians from different universities, including people like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ctu.mrc.ac.uk/about-us/senior-staff/ian-white/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ian White&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/carpenter.james&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;James Carpenter&lt;/a&gt; from UCL and the LSHTM. It was really an amazing experience to meet so many people working in different stats area but with a common passion about missing data methods (also mine!). From what I understood this series of meetings (called &amp;ldquo;MiDIA&amp;rdquo;) have been held since years but do not have a very regular schedule due to people being busy I guess, which makes totally sense. Not sure when the next one will be held by no I am definitely looking forward to the next meetings!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/kFBJt0yqZD315EFJiJ/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would also like to highlight a recent tweet from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/priment/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UCL PRIMENT CTU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Vacancy?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Vacancy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;Come join our team of health economists! &lt;br&gt;Closing date: 15 March 2020&lt;br&gt;Apply here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/IUg8JIeANX&#34;&gt;https://t.co/IUg8JIeANX&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/clinicaltrials?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#clinicaltrials&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/healtheconomics?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#healtheconomics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Priment Clinical Trials Unit (@PRIMENT_UCL) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/PRIMENT_UCL/status/1230124818244173824?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;which advertises a new position as health economist in our HEART group for performing health economics using data from clinical trials. I would encourage anyone interested in some good applied health economic work to apply for this position. Deadline 15 March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/kHZu4LDtvpY63RT1He/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To conclude, I would also like to say that I have done some updates to this website. From the inclusion of new tutorials on the use of &lt;code&gt;JAGS&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;STAN&lt;/code&gt; on different statistical topics, to a restyle of the website. In particular I had fun by playing around with some &lt;code&gt;Markdown&lt;/code&gt; code to add new features, e.g. customised alert notes and emoji that you may find on my &lt;a href=&#34;/authors/agabrio/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt;, for example. This took me so much time but I am quite satisfied with the result if I may say so. You really never stop learning new things!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally here ...</title>
      <link>/post/update-february/update-february/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-february/update-february/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The new year is finally taking off for me and I have a couple of updates. First, I would like to remind everyone about the exciting new course &amp;ldquo;understanding health economics in clinical trials&amp;rdquo; that me and
the rest of our research team &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HEART&lt;/a&gt; have put together to support the dissemination of health economics among all people involved in the design and analysis of clinical trials.
I look forward to deliver this one-day short course together with my colleagues from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/epidemiology-health-care/research/pcph&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UCL PCPH department&lt;/a&gt; which will be structured into different sessions
during the day of Feb 11th at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/comprehensive-clinical-trials-unit/contact-us&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UCL CCTU&lt;/a&gt; - 2nd Floor, 90 High Holborn, London. The course is specifically intended for those who would like to know more
about health economics, which has become an important component in the design, analysis and most crucially, for the funding approval of clinical trials. The course will focus on the following aspects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A short intorduction to the basic concepts of health economics and why these can be relevent to different people&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A review of different types of intruments and tools used to collect health economic data in clinical trials&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A quick look at decision models with some examples&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A summary of the typical results from health economic analyses and how to interpret them&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course is still in its pilot form and therfore it is free of charge. If there are still places available, you are very welcome to join and give us your feedback!.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/RMTQiRYAuvvJb1k6al/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I am happy to announce that my recent paper about the use of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02664763.2020.1723506&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bayesian Hierarchical Models for the Prediction of Volleyball Results&lt;/a&gt; has finally
been published on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/loi/cjas20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Journal of Applied Statistics&lt;/a&gt;. I am really proud of this paper as it is my first solo paper publiched and because I have always been very invested in the general topic of
predicting sport results using probability models. To be able to publish something about this based on my own efforts is very rewarding in terms of the (small) contribution to research that I hope I was able to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/l0He0cVv8lGggpruo/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have submitted an abstract to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://euhea.eu/welcome_conference_2020.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2020 European Health Economics Association Conference&lt;/a&gt;, which this year will be held in Oslo, Norway.&lt;br /&gt;
I have now to patiently wait for the review of the abstracts and see if my work made it, either as an oral presenation or as a poster. Fingers crossed!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let us do some work</title>
      <link>/post/update2-january/update-january2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update2-january/update-january2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After the terrible start of this year, things are going ok now and I am quite busy with different projects that I left a bit behind. First, I can confirm that me and my colleagues from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HEART group&lt;/a&gt;
are going to give an introductory course to health economic evaluations next month for different groups of people from academia and clinical trial units. The course has been generally structured based on our &amp;ldquo;pilot&amp;rdquo; we gave last year (which went really well by the way)
and involves many different topics that will cover the entire day of February 11th. The attending list is already full and thw waiting list is also quite big; happy to see so much interest in economic evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I will give a talk at the PRIMENT statistics and health economics and methodology seminar about an on-going project on missing data in trial-based analysis on Tuesday 28th, at UCL &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/priment/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PRIMENT CTU&lt;/a&gt;.
I am really happy to be back at these seminars which I feel I really nice and where you have the opportunity to interact with people from different backgrounds and job positions who may give some useful feedback on my work. Hopefully,
people will find my research interesting!. I would also like to mention the fact that one of my HEART colleague, &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=MCCLE13&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Marie&lt;/a&gt;, will give another talk at the same seminar just before me.
Her topic is the economic analysis plan for a trial she has been involved with and I think she is really good, so may worth check her presentaiton out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, I have finalised a long-waited submission for a paper which has been discussed, written and re-written many times. I really hope we can get some useful feedback on it as
I personally worked very hard to keep this work alive. Let see if my efforts have not been in vain and fingers crossed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/4KxeicCUTvhrW/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, as a side note, I have recently bought a new book on missing data called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.springer.com/gp/book/9780387324487&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Semiparametric Thoery and Missing Data&lt;/a&gt; by Tsiatis, which looks very interesting.
To be honest, the book is quite technical with many theoretical concpets and proofs which sometimes I find hard to follow. However, so far it gives a nice introduction to semiparametric models and I look forward to see
how it approaches the missing data topic from a non likelihood-based approach. If you are into non/semiparametric statistics and want to find out more about this, I recommend the reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, more work is also coming up in the next weeks and some of this is not going to be very enjoyable, I think. Anyway, let us go through this busy period at our best and see how things will go.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
