<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>News on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/tags/news/</link>
    <description>Recent content in News on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>`{year}`</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lockdown</title>
      <link>/post/update-march/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-march/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have to admit, although I expected some fear to spread because of the virus which is currently and quickly infecting the world, I was surprised by the frenzy surrounding
us, especially in my homecountry (Italy) and particularly in my parents&amp;rsquo; region which is at the moment under lockdown. I will also probably cancel my planned trip home for Eastern
and perhaps also after that since the situations is still unclear and I may be unable to come back to the UK in the short time. This is pretty scary to all the people living in those
territories, who are now forbidden to have any sort of public meeting and are strongly recommended to stay at home. I am afraid this will not be enough to stop the virus 
from spreading but of course it is useful as it is the only way we have if we want to contain it. The hope is that by summer time the heath will reduce the ability of the virus
to spread and give us some time to come up with a possible vaccine in the next months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have already been attempts to estimate the fatality ratio of the virus using statistical methods. Here I post the tweet from Andrew Gelman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Post Edited: Coronavirus age-specific fatality ratio, estimated using Stan, and (attempting) to account for underreporting of cases and the time delay to death.  Now with data and code.  And now a link to another paper (also with data and code). &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/CSHnXRMtyp&#34;&gt;https://t.co/CSHnXRMtyp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Gelman (@StatModeling) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/StatModeling/status/1236845267275702273?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March 9, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which refers to epidemiologists who tried to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.03.04.20031104v1.full.pdf&#34;&gt;STAN&lt;/a&gt; for achieving this objective, although an additional reference
to another work based on the use of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.02.14.20023127v1&#34;&gt;differential equation analysis&lt;/a&gt; is also made. However, results 
are still preliminary and subject to limitations for the type of data and assumptions used. From a statistical perspective I am sure this new epidemic will be interesting to
study and I guess lots of funding will be devoted to analyse the upcoming data to get a better idea of the actual threat it represents for the people. I am not an epidemiologist,
so I do not have a big statistical interest in this, although I am pretty much worried as any other person. Hopefully, this will become clearer as time passes and let us just hope
the number of deaths will not be very high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry about talking about this here, but from time to time I would also like to highlight was is currently happening around me. As for my research, nothing has changed much for me
at the moment and life as usual continues with another busy upcoming period with lots of boring meetings, reports and standard analyses to do, but hopefully I can also save some time
to do some methodological work. I am also waiting for the decision about my abstract which I submitted to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cfp.euhea.eu/conf/euhea2020&#34;&gt;EuHEA conference 2020&lt;/a&gt; and which is supposed to
be held in Oslo this July. I really hope I have a chance to presenting my work there as I have never been to this specific health economic conference. Fingers crossed! Of course, 
nobody knows what will happen from here till July and much is to be discussed also with respect to how the spreading of the virus may affect everyone&amp;rsquo;s schedule in the next months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/3ohhwxaw5OlElXzv8s/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something old, something new, something borrowed, something blue</title>
      <link>/post/update2-february/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update2-february/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The moment for the second edition of the HEART&amp;rsquo;s one-day introductory course to health economics arrived at last! The course, led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=RMHUN48&#34;&gt;Rachael Hunter&lt;/a&gt; and called &amp;ldquo;Understanding health economics in clinical trials&amp;rdquo;, took place on Tuesday 11 February and was prepared in collaboration between the HEART group and the Institute of Clinical Trials and Methodology (ICTM). I believe this second edition of the course was a success both in terms of the quality/quantity of the material covered during the six sessions throughout the day, as well as in terms of the positive feedback we received from the participants. Also, this time a new HEART member (&lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=MCCLE13&#34;&gt;Marie&lt;/a&gt;) joined the group and very nicely delivered the session about patient reported outcome measures (PROMs), engaging in nice discussions with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a couple of personal notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I recently attended a very interesting meeting about missing data methodology which was held by an international group of very talented senior and junior statisticians from different universities, including people like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ctu.mrc.ac.uk/about-us/senior-staff/ian-white/&#34;&gt;Ian White&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/carpenter.james&#34;&gt;James Carpenter&lt;/a&gt; from UCL and the LSHTM. It was really an amazing experience to meet so many people working in different stats area but with a common passion about missing data methods (also mine!). From what I understood this series of meetings (called &amp;ldquo;MiDIA&amp;rdquo;) have been held since years but do not have a very regular schedule due to people being busy I guess, which makes totally sense. Not sure when the next one will be held but now I am definitely looking forward to the next meetings!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/kFBJt0yqZD315EFJiJ/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would also like to highlight a recent tweet from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/priment/&#34;&gt;UCL PRIMENT CTU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Vacancy?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Vacancy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;Come join our team of health economists! &lt;br&gt;Closing date: 15 March 2020&lt;br&gt;Apply here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/IUg8JIeANX&#34;&gt;https://t.co/IUg8JIeANX&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/clinicaltrials?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#clinicaltrials&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/healtheconomics?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#healtheconomics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Priment Clinical Trials Unit (@PRIMENT_UCL) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/PRIMENT_UCL/status/1230124818244173824?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which advertises a new position as health economist in our HEART group for performing health economics using data from clinical trials. I would encourage anyone interested in some good applied health economic work to apply for this position. Deadline 15 March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/kHZu4LDtvpY63RT1He/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To conclude, I would also like to say that I have done some updates to this website. From the inclusion of new tutorials on the use of &lt;a href=&#34;/jags/&#34;&gt;JAGS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;/stan/&#34;&gt;STAN&lt;/a&gt; on different statistical topics, to a restyle of the website. In particular I had fun by playing around with some &lt;code&gt;Markdown&lt;/code&gt; code to add new features, e.g. customised alert notes and emoji, for example. Somthing like this:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alertqueen alertqueen-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;h4 class=&#34;alertqueen-heading;&#34;&gt;&amp;#9819; Queen&#39;s note! &amp;#9819; &lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
    I 👍 $\rm \LaTeX$ very much.
        &lt;hr&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This took me so much time but I am quite satisfied with the result if I may say so. You really never stop learning new things!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally here ...</title>
      <link>/post/update-february/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-february/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The new year is finally taking off for me and I have a couple of updates. First, I would like to remind everyone about the exciting new course &amp;ldquo;understanding health economics in clinical trials&amp;rdquo; that me and 
the rest of our research team &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;HEART&lt;/a&gt; have put together to support the dissemination of health economics among all people involved in the design and analysis of clinical trials.
I look forward to deliver this one-day short course together with my colleagues from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/epidemiology-health-care/research/pcph&#34;&gt;UCL PCPH department&lt;/a&gt; which will be structured into different sessions
during the day of Feb 11th at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/comprehensive-clinical-trials-unit/contact-us&#34;&gt;UCL CCTU&lt;/a&gt; - 2nd Floor, 90 High Holborn, London. The course is specifically intended for those who would like to know more 
about health economics, which has become an important component in the design, analysis and most crucially, for the funding approval of clinical trials. The course will focus on the following aspects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short intorduction to the basic concepts of health economics and why these can be relevent to different people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A review of different types of intruments and tools used to collect health economic data in clinical trials&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick look at decision models with some examples&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A summary of the typical results from health economic analyses and how to interpret them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is still in its pilot form and therfore it is free of charge. If there are still places available, you are very welcome to join and give us your feedback!.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/RMTQiRYAuvvJb1k6al/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I am happy to announce that my recent paper about the use of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02664763.2020.1723506&#34;&gt;Bayesian Hierarchical Models for the Prediction of Volleyball Results&lt;/a&gt; has finally 
been published on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/loi/cjas20&#34;&gt;Journal of Applied Statistics&lt;/a&gt;. I am really proud of this paper as it is my first solo paper publiched and because I have always been very invested in the general topic of 
predicting sport results using probability models. To be able to publish something about this based on my own efforts is very rewarding in terms of the (small) contribution to research that I hope I was able to provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/l0He0cVv8lGggpruo/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have submitted an abstract to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://euhea.eu/welcome_conference_2020.html&#34;&gt;2020 European Health Economics Association Conference&lt;/a&gt;, which this year will be held in Oslo, Norway.&lt;br&gt;
I have now to patiently wait for the review of the abstracts and see if my work made it, either as an oral presenation or as a poster. Fingers crossed!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let us do some work</title>
      <link>/post/update-january2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-january2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After the terrible start of this year, things are going ok now and I am quite busy with different projects that I left a bit behind. First, I can confirm that me and my colleagues from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;HEART group&lt;/a&gt;
are going to give an introductory course to health economic evaluations next month for different groups of people from academia and clinical trial units. The course has been generally structured based on our &amp;ldquo;pilot&amp;rdquo; we gave last year (which went really well by the way)
and involves many different topics that will cover the entire day of February 11th. The attending list is already full and thw waiting list is also quite big; happy to see so much interest in economic evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I will give a talk at the PRIMENT statistics and health economics and methodology seminar about an on-going project on missing data in trial-based analysis on Tuesday 28th, at UCL &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/priment/&#34;&gt;PRIMENT CTU&lt;/a&gt;.
I am really happy to be back at these seminars which I feel I really nice and where you have the opportunity to interact with people from different backgrounds and job positions who may give some useful feedback on my work. Hopefully, 
people will find my research interesting!. I would also like to mention the fact that one of my HEART colleague, &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=MCCLE13&#34;&gt;Marie&lt;/a&gt;, will give another talk at the same seminar just before me.
Her topic is the economic analysis plan for a trial she has been involved with and I think she is really good, so may worth check her presentaiton out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, I have finalised a long-waited submission for a paper which has been discussed, written and re-written many times. I really hope we can get some useful feedback on it as 
I personally worked very hard to keep this work alive. Let see if my efforts have not been in vain and fingers crossed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/4KxeicCUTvhrW/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fourth, as a side note, I have recently bought a new book on missing data called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.springer.com/gp/book/9780387324487&#34;&gt;Semiparametric Thoery and Missing Data&lt;/a&gt; by Tsiatis, which looks very interesting.
To be honest, the book is quite technical with many theoretical concpets and proofs which sometimes I find hard to follow. However, so far it gives a nice introduction to semiparametric models and I look forward to see 
how it approaches the missing data topic from a non likelihood-based approach. If you are into non/semiparametric statistics and want to find out more about this, I recommend the reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, more work is also coming up in the next weeks and some of this is not going to be very enjoyable, I think. Anyway, let us go through this busy period at our best and see how things will go.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not a very good start...</title>
      <link>/post/update-january/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-january/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After some nice holiday break, I came back to work ready for an exciting 2020 &amp;hellip; or so I thought. Unfortunately, I have recently been caught by a terrible flu which forced me to postpone my flight back to London of a week. 
The worst part is that I was basically a dead corpse moving around with high fever and an awful condition for more than 4 days. It was quite a bad experience which I rarely had in my life. I am just glad I survived this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/12Eo3WBLbH9HRS/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to more interesting news. Before my cursed period, I was smart enough to work on different things and I am happy to announce a new update for my &lt;code&gt;missingHE&lt;/code&gt; package, which is available both on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/AnGabrio/missingHE&#34;&gt;GitHub page&lt;/a&gt; and on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/missingHE&#34;&gt;CRAN repository&lt;/a&gt;. 
Its new version is 1.3.2 and has the nice addition of making available more choices for the parametric distributions that can be selected in all main functions of the package to handle missing data in trial-based economic evaluations. In particular, it is now possible
to choose among new probability distributions for the health outcomes, including continuous (Gamma, Weibull, Exponential, Logistic), discrete (Poisson, Negative Binomial) and binary (Bernoulli) distributions. These may be useful when the analysis is not based on utilities scores but some other
types of effects, such as survival time, number of events or binary outcomes. I have also included some examples for each type of outcome in the MenSS dataset (available directly once installed the package on your machine) so that people can play around with the new distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another good news is that the last paper written with &lt;a href=&#34;http://users.stat.ufl.edu/~daniels/&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; about missing data handling in economic evaluations will soon be publiched in the February issue of JRSSA, which will make the final and official version of the article that can be cited, I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, an announcement about the one-day course I am holding together with my mates from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;HEART group&lt;/a&gt; about an introduction to economic evaluations to people who are not familiar with health economics. The course will take place next month, I believe on Feb 11th, 
in central London (soon an update about the exact location) and, as the previous edition, I am happy to see that all spots have been taken and everything is sold out (well, to be precise the course is free &amp;hellip;). Need to meet up with the others to make the last changes and prepare the slides but I am quite excited about this, given also the good response we got last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I am (hopefully) ready to start the new year and there are many things already piling up on my list of things to do in the next days. Let&amp;rsquo;s try again 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Too many things, again....</title>
      <link>/post/update-november/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-november/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I did not have much time to post anything this month until now as it has been a quite busy period. I have been involved in many different works and I have also involved other people in what I think could be some very interesting new projects. Not that I complain about having many different things to do (most of them are actually cool) but doing everything in a short period is not the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of things have come/are coming up. First, I have seriously started working on the coding of a decision model for some health economic evaluation project I have been involved in since last year. Everything seems ok after I spent lots of days and time fixing some small bugs in my code. I am about half way through the model and I hope I will be able to finish it before Christmas (I doubt it though).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I have finished reviewing an interesting paper about some new methods for improving current practice for dealing with missing data, which I kinda enjoy reading (very good!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, I would like to quickly summarise my first experience at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ispor.org/conferences-education/conferences/past-conferences/ispor-europe-2019&#34;&gt;ISPOR Europe&lt;/a&gt; in Copenhagen. I was really excited to attend this conference which, as expected, revealed itself as huge with people coming from all over the world and with many interesting sessions and discussion topics. I had the chance to meet new and old people, such as professor &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.york.ac.uk/che/staff/research/andrea-manca/&#34;&gt;Andrea Manca&lt;/a&gt; and the always very kind &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ohe.org/about-us/meet-team/chris-sampson&#34;&gt;Chris Sampson&lt;/a&gt; for whom I was like a stalker asking for more and more information about himself and his work. I also met some of my old collegues from MapiGroup, now under &lt;a href=&#34;https://iconplc.com/&#34;&gt;ICON plc&lt;/a&gt;. It was very fun to hang out with these old friends and see what they have been up to during this time. Among them, I gladly caught up with my dear friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iqce.uni-hamburg.de/people/iqce-fellows/ryan-pulleyblank.html&#34;&gt;Ryan Pulleyblank&lt;/a&gt;, now doing a PhD at the University of Southern Denmark. My poster was a success with (unexpectedly) many people stopping by and asking for more information on my work. I was genuinely surprised by this as ISPOR is mostly a conference dedicated to companies rather than academic works and networking. To sum up, it was a very nice and fun experience and despite the level of statistical methodology was not particularly high I enjoyed my time there and I also had the chance to visit Copenhagen for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as a side note, I have found the time to upload on my arXiv page a nice application of &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.08791&#34;&gt;Bayesian hierarchical models for the prediction of volleyball matches&lt;/a&gt; which I have been working on the past summer, taking inspiration from the work of Gianluca about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/02664760802684177?journalCode=cjas20&#34;&gt;predicting football macthes&lt;/a&gt;. I hope my work can turn out in something cool as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/oWA8lD03GUew8/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all for the moment but soon I will be heading back to another quite busy period for me. I hope this will be the last for some time, especially given that Christmas is coming and I would like to have some free time to properly enjoy this period, which I really like, even more than Christmas itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copenhagen, I am coming ...</title>
      <link>/post/update3-october/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update3-october/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally the time of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ispor.org/conferences-education/conferences/upcoming-conferences/ispor-europe-2019&#34;&gt;ISPOR Europe 2019&lt;/a&gt; has arrived and I will depart in a few days for 
Copenhagen, where the conference is held this year. I am actually looking forward to this as I am curious to see what type of conference ISPOR is, that is, whether I will be able to find
some interesting works and have some &amp;ldquo;applied statistics&amp;rdquo;-related discussions or the attention is more placed on &amp;ldquo;economics and clinical&amp;rdquo; matters. From what I heard by other people who 
routinely attend the conference, there should be a bit of both sides, even though I really hope I will be able to see some intersting methods and engage in discussion with some authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the conference is mainly related to address the needs of pharmaceutical and consultancy companies, but I hope I will be able to see some familiar faces there. Well, to be
honest I know that some people I already know are going, which is good considering that their work is really cool. As for me, I will present the same work that I showed at ICTMC 2019 (some slides available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.luminpdf.com/viewer/5dbd43939a40480018633f2e&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;),
but this time in the format of a poster, of which I am kind of very proud in terms of the final output, if I may say so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this nice event, there are many things coming up when I will be back from the conference, which I really need to start working on. Mostly, these are related to some
routine work for some trial analyses at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/priment/&#34;&gt;PRIMENT&lt;/a&gt;, which by the way is advertising a new health economist &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/BWK840/research-fellow-in-health-economics&#34;&gt;job vacancy&lt;/a&gt; for those who might be interested. 
Other tasks include writing down and code a decision model on which I have been working since ages, papers review, other collaborations with different people, starting my co-supervison for a new PhD student at stats and, after I can find some free time, do some reasearch work on my beloved missing data. 
Am I ready? not sure about that &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/fy0gLJtIkZj8I/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conferences updates and news</title>
      <link>/post/update2-october/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update2-october/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a quick update about some talks I gave/am about to give to advertise my research work. The one in Brighton, which I gave a couple of weeks a go at &lt;a href=&#34;https://ictmc2019.com/&#34;&gt;ICTMC&lt;/a&gt;, went really well and I was glad to hear that some people were very interested in what I presented. For more info, here a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.luminpdf.com/viewer/5daad5f7ad8625001932b9a4&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to my presentation about missing data methods for trial-based economic evaluations that I discussed.
Honestly, since the conference was mainly directed towards people working in clinical trials, I did not expect a huge interest in the use of Bayesian methods for economic evaluations, but apparently (and I am happy about that) I was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the chance to chat a bit with few people that I did not know, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bristol.ac.uk/social-community-medicine/people/william-hollingworth/overview.html&#34;&gt;William Hollingworth&lt;/a&gt; from Bristol and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ndorms.ox.ac.uk/team/ines-rombach&#34;&gt;Ines Rombach&lt;/a&gt; from Oxford, with whom I had very nice conversations about my work and other interesting topics.
I was also glad to meet some known faces, including the always lovely &lt;a href=&#34;https://cheme.bangor.ac.uk/CatrinPlumptonBiography.php&#34;&gt;Catrin Plumpton&lt;/a&gt; from Bangor University, who I met for the first time at HESG this summer and with whom I share the interest in missing data methods (even though she is a STATA and multiple imputation user, sadly). 
I am also glad that I met my previous PhD secondary supervisor, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/mason.alexina&#34;&gt;Alexina Mason&lt;/a&gt;, with whom it is always a pleasure to talk with. Unfortunately, we both missed the talk of each other becuase of time problems but it was good to catch up with her again. I am also sad that I could
not attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/leurent.baptiste&#34;&gt;Baptiste&lt;/a&gt;&amp;lsquo;s presentation which was the last day of the conference (I had to leave the same day of my talk, the first day) and I was not also able to actually meet him. I hope we will be able to see him soon at some other conference in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/YATNr2oXRo0IE/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this past experience, I am now looking forward to meet new people at my next conference at the Bella Center in Copenhagen (thumbnail) where this year &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ispor.org/conferences-education/conferences/upcoming-conferences/ispor-europe-2019&#34;&gt;ISPOR Europe 2019&lt;/a&gt; will be held. However, I believe this will be a much larger conference and therefore I will probably not have many chances to talk with people as I did at ICTMC.
Plus I am only preseting a poster this time, so it will be less likely that some people will actually notice my work, especially given the typically huge amount of presenters of this type of conferences. In the wrost case, I will enjoy Copenhagen and meet up with some old friends who live in Denmark and who will come at ISPOR to present some other work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More good news...</title>
      <link>/post/update-october/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-october/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have got two news coming up. First, the paper I wrote with Michael and Gianluca on Bayesian methdos for longitudinal data in trial-based economic evaluations has finally been published as early view on &lt;a href=&#34;https://rss.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/rssa.12522&#34;&gt;JRSSA&lt;/a&gt;. As I said in some earlier posts, I am super happy about this collaboration and I hope I can continue working on similar projects in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I will soon give a talk about this work at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ictmc2019.com/&#34;&gt;ICTMC&lt;/a&gt; conference in Brighton, next Monday. This will be the first time at this conference and unfortunately I will only be able to remain around for one day as I need to go back to London pretty soon. I hope I will be able to enjoy my day at the conference, even though I will miss the talks of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/leurent.baptiste&#34;&gt;Baptiste&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/mason.alexina&#34;&gt;Alexina&lt;/a&gt; which are scheduled for the last day of the conference. I hope I can at least have a quick chat with them the day I am around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/efDT7dqlF5N2LVHG8C/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also excited to visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brighton&#34;&gt;Brighton&lt;/a&gt;, since many people keep telling me that I should go and visit this sort of british version of &amp;ldquo;Rimini&amp;rdquo;. To be honest, I do not expect to find a nice wheather, given that in this period it is raining a lot in London, but I hope I will be lucky and get the only sunny day of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have started a rubric called &lt;a href=&#34;https://agabrioblog.onrender.com/missingdata/&#34;&gt;missing data&lt;/a&gt; on my website, where I try to describe some of the most popular methods to handle missing data and to provide some references for anyone who could be interested in this field. I am really fascinated by statistical methods for dealing with missingness, perhaps because it was the main focus of my PhD, but I am eager to review different methods and see if I can find something really interesting. Of course, to complete this it will take more time, which I hope I will be able to find in the next months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
