<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Christmas on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/categories/christmas/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Christmas on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/categories/christmas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Too many things, again....</title>
      <link>/post/update-november/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-november/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I did not have much time to post anything this month until now as it has been a quite busy period. I have been involved in many different works and I have also involved other people in what I think could be some very interesting new projects. Not that I complain about having many different things to do (most of them are actually cool) but doing everything in a short period is not the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of things have come/are coming up. First, I have seriously started working on the coding of a decision model for some health economic evaluation project I have been involved in since last year. Everything seems ok after I spent lots of days and time fixing some small bugs in my code. I am about half way through the model and I hope I will be able to finish it before Christmas (I doubt it though).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I have finished reviewing an interesting paper about some new methods for improving current practice for dealing with missing data, which I kinda enjoy reading (very good!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, I would like to quickly summarise my first experience at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ispor.org/conferences-education/conferences/past-conferences/ispor-europe-2019&#34;&gt;ISPOR Europe&lt;/a&gt; in Copenhagen. I was really excited to attend this conference which, as expected, revealed itself as huge with people coming from all over the world and with many interesting sessions and discussion topics. I had the chance to meet new and old people, such as professor &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.york.ac.uk/che/staff/research/andrea-manca/&#34;&gt;Andrea Manca&lt;/a&gt; and the always very kind &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ohe.org/about-us/meet-team/chris-sampson&#34;&gt;Chris Sampson&lt;/a&gt; for whom I was like a stalker asking for more and more information about himself and his work. I also met some of my old collegues from MapiGroup, now under &lt;a href=&#34;https://iconplc.com/&#34;&gt;ICON plc&lt;/a&gt;. It was very fun to hang out with these old friends and see what they have been up to during this time. Among them, I gladly caught up with my dear friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iqce.uni-hamburg.de/people/iqce-fellows/ryan-pulleyblank.html&#34;&gt;Ryan Pulleyblank&lt;/a&gt;, now doing a PhD at the University of Southern Denmark. My poster was a success with (unexpectedly) many people stopping by and asking for more information on my work. I was genuinely surprised by this as ISPOR is mostly a conference dedicated to companies rather than academic works and networking. To sum up, it was a very nice and fun experience and despite the level of statistical methodology was not particularly high I enjoyed my time there and I also had the chance to visit Copenhagen for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as a side note, I have found the time to upload on my arXiv page a nice application of &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.08791&#34;&gt;Bayesian hierarchical models for the prediction of volleyball matches&lt;/a&gt; which I have been working on the past summer, taking inspiration from the work of Gianluca about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/02664760802684177?journalCode=cjas20&#34;&gt;predicting football macthes&lt;/a&gt;. I hope my work can turn out in something cool as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/oWA8lD03GUew8/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all for the moment but soon I will be heading back to another quite busy period for me. I hope this will be the last for some time, especially given that Christmas is coming and I would like to have some free time to properly enjoy this period, which I really like, even more than Christmas itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
