<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conferences on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/tags/conferences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conferences on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/conferences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Copenhagen, I am coming ...</title>
      <link>/post/update3-october/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update3-october/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally the time of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ispor.org/conferences-education/conferences/upcoming-conferences/ispor-europe-2019&#34;&gt;ISPOR Europe 2019&lt;/a&gt; has arrived and I will depart in a few days for 
Copenhagen, where the conference is held this year. I am actually looking forward to this as I am curious to see what type of conference ISPOR is, that is, whether I will be able to find
some interesting works and have some &amp;ldquo;applied statistics&amp;rdquo;-related discussions or the attention is more placed on &amp;ldquo;economics and clinical&amp;rdquo; matters. From what I heard by other people who 
routinely attend the conference, there should be a bit of both sides, even though I really hope I will be able to see some intersting methods and engage in discussion with some authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the conference is mainly related to address the needs of pharmaceutical and consultancy companies, but I hope I will be able to see some familiar faces there. Well, to be
honest I know that some people I already know are going, which is good considering that their work is really cool. As for me, I will present the same work that I showed at ICTMC 2019 (some slides available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.luminpdf.com/viewer/5dbd43939a40480018633f2e&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;),
but this time in the format of a poster, of which I am kind of very proud in terms of the final output, if I may say so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this nice event, there are many things coming up when I will be back from the conference, which I really need to start working on. Mostly, these are related to some
routine work for some trial analyses at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/priment/&#34;&gt;PRIMENT&lt;/a&gt;, which by the way is advertising a new health economist &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/BWK840/research-fellow-in-health-economics&#34;&gt;job vacancy&lt;/a&gt; for those who might be interested. 
Other tasks include writing down and code a decision model on which I have been working since ages, papers review, other collaborations with different people, starting my co-supervison for a new PhD student at stats and, after I can find some free time, do some reasearch work on my beloved missing data. 
Am I ready? not sure about that &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/fy0gLJtIkZj8I/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
