<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bayesian Modelling on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/tags/bayesian-modelling/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bayesian Modelling on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/bayesian-modelling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Hierarchical Models for the Prediction of Volleyball Results</title>
      <link>/project/volleyball/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/volleyball/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;modelling-framework&#34;&gt;Modelling Framework&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We extend and adapt the modelling frameworks typically used for the analysis of football data and propose a novel Bayesian hierarchical modelling framework for the analysis and
prediction of volleyball results in regular seasons. Three different sub-models or &amp;ldquo;modules&amp;rdquo; form our framework: (1) The module of the observed number of points scored by the two opposing teams in a match ($y_h$ and $y_a$);
(2) the module of the binary indicator for the number of sets played ($d^s$); (3) the module of the binary indicator for the winner of the match ($d^m$).
These three modules are jointly modelled using a flexible Bayesian parametric approach, which allows to fully propagate the uncertainty for each unobserved quantity
and to assess the predictive performance of the model in a relatively easy way. In the following, we describe the notation and the model used in each of the three modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;module-1-modelling-the-scoring-intensity&#34;&gt;Module 1: Modelling the Scoring Intensity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first module of the framework, we model the number of points scored by the home and away team in the $i$-th match of the season $\boldsymbol y=(y&lt;em&gt;{hi},y&lt;/em&gt;{ai})$
using two independent Poisson distributions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
y_{hi} \sim Poisson(\theta_{hi}),
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
y_{ai} \sim Poisson(\theta_{ai}),
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;conditionally on the set of parameters $\boldsymbol \theta=(\theta_{hi},\theta_{ai})$, representing the scoring intensity in the $i$-th match for the home and away team, respectively.
These parameters are then modelled using the log-linear regressions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
log(\theta_{hi}) =\mu + \lambda + att_{h(i)} + def_{a(i)},
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
log(\theta_{ai}) =\mu + att_{a(i)} + def_{h(i)},
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which corresponds to a Poisson log-linear model. Within these formulae, $\mu$ is a constant, while $\lambda$ can be identified as the home effect and represents the advantage
for the team hosting the game which is typically assumed to be constant for all the teams and throughout the season.
The overall offensive and defensive performances of the $k$-th team is captured by the parameters $att$ and $def$, whose nested indexes $h(i), a(i)=1,\ldots,K$ identify
the home and away team in the $i$-th game of the season, where $K$ denotes the total number of the teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then expand the modelling framework to incorporate match-specific statistics related to the offensive and defensive performances of the home and away teams.
More specifically, the effects associated with the attack intensity of the home teams and the defence effect of the away teams are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
att_{h(i)} =\alpha_{0h(i)} + \alpha_{1h(i)}att^{eff}_{hi} + \alpha_{2h(i)}ser^{eff}_{hi},
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
def_{a(i)} =\beta_{0a(i)} + \beta_{1a(i)}def^{eff}_{ai} + \beta_{2a(i)}blo^{eff}_{ai}.
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We omit the index $i$ from the terms to the left-hand side of the above formulae to ease notation, i.e. $att_{h(i)}=att_{h(i)i}$ and $def_{a(i)}=def_{a(i)i}$.
The overall offensive effect of the home teams is a function of a baseline team specific parameter $\alpha_{0h(i)}$, and the attack and serve efficiencies of the home team,
whose impact is captured by the parameters $\alpha_{1h(i)}$ and $\alpha_{2h(i)}$. The overall defensive effect of the away team is a function of a baseline team-specific
parameter $\beta_{0a(i)}$, and the defence and block efficiencies of the away team, whose impact is captured by the parameters $\beta_{1a(i)}$ and $\beta_{2a(i)}$, respectively.
Similarly, the effects associated with the attack intensity of the away teams and the defence effect of the home teams are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
att_{a(i)} =\alpha_{0a(i)} + \alpha_{1a(i)}att^{eff}_{ai}+ \alpha_{2a(i)}ser^{eff}_{ai},
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
def_{h(i)} =\beta_{0h(i)} + \beta_{1h(i)}def^{eff}_{hi}+ \beta_{2h(i)}blo^{eff}_{hi},
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve identifiability of the model, a set of parametric constraints needs to be imposed. We impose &lt;em&gt;sum-to-zero&lt;/em&gt; constraints on the team-specific parameters, i.e. we set $\sum_{k=1}^{K}\alpha_{jk}=0$ and $\sum_{k=1}^{K}\beta_{jk}=0$, for $k=1,\ldots,K$ and $j=(0,1,2)$.
Under this set of constraints, the overall offensive and defensive effects of the teams are expressed as departures from a team of average offensive and defensive performance.
Within a Bayesian framework, prior distributions need to be specified for all random parameters in the model. Weakly informative Normal distributions centred at $0$ with a relatively large variances are specified for the fixed effect parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;module-2-modelling-the-probability-of-playing-5-sets&#34;&gt;Module 2: Modelling the Probability of Playing 5 Sets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second module, we explicitly model the chance of playing $5$ sets in the $i$-th match of the season, i.e. the sum of the sets won by the home ($s_{hi}$)
and away ($s_{ai}$) team is equal to $5$. This is necessary when generating predictions in order to correctly assign the points to the winning/losing teams throughout
the season and evaluate the rankings of the teams at the end of the season.
We model the indicator variable $d^s_{i}$, taking value $1$ if $5$ sets were played in the $i-$th match and $0$ otherwise, using a Bernoulli distribution&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
d^s_{i}:=\mathbb{I}(s_{hi}+s_{ai}=5)\sim\mbox{Bernoulli}(\pi^s_{i}),
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
logit(\pi^s_{i})= \gamma_0 + \gamma_1y_{hi} + \gamma_2y_{ai}.&lt;br /&gt;
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;module-3-modelling-the-probability-of-winning-the-match&#34;&gt;Module 3: Modelling the Probability of Winning the Match&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last module deals with the chance of the home team to win the $i$-th match, i.e. the total number of sets won by the home team  ($s_{hi}$)
is larger than that of the away team ($s_{ai}$) &amp;ndash; we note that we could have also equivalently decided to model the chance of the away team to win the $i$-th match.
This part of the model is again necessary when predicting the results for future matches, since the team associated with the higher number of points scored in the $i$-th
match may not correspond to the winning team.
We model the indicator variable $d^m_{i}$, taking value $1$ if the home team won the $i-$th match and $0$ otherwise, using another Bernoulli distribution&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
d^m_{i}:=\mathbb{I}(s_{hi}&amp;gt;s_{ai}) \sim\mbox{Bernoulli}(\pi^m_{i}),
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
logit(\pi^m_{i})= \eta_0 + \eta_1y_{hi} + \eta_2y_{ai} + \eta_3 d^s_i.
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next figure shows a graphical representation of the modelling framework proposed.&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/framework_volley.jpg&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Graphical representation of the modelling framework.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The framework corresponds to a joint distribution for all the observed quantities which are explicitly modelled.
This is factored into the product of the marginal distribution of the total number of points scored by the two teams in each match, Module 1 &amp;ndash; $p(\boldsymbol y)$,
the conditional distribution of the probability of playing $5$ sets in a match given $\boldsymbol y$, Module 2 &amp;ndash; $p(d^s_i \mid \boldsymbol y)$,
and the conditional probability of winning the match given $\boldsymbol y$ and $d^s_i$, Module 3 &amp;ndash; $p(d^m_i\mid \boldsymbol y, d^s_i)$.
Module 1 also includes the different in-game statistics as covariates in the model. These are related to the either the offensive (serve and attack efficiency)
or defensive (defence and block efficiency) effects of the home and away teams in each match of the season, and are respectively denoted in the graph as
$\boldsymbol x^{att}_{ti}=(ser^{eff}_{ti}, att^{eff}_{ti})$ and $\boldsymbol x^{def}_{ti}=(def^{eff}_{ti}, blo^{eff}_{ti})$ to ease notation, for $t=(h,a)$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;accounting-for-the-multilevel-correlation&#34;&gt;Accounting for the multilevel correlation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Although the individual-level correlation between the observable variables $y_{hi}$ and $y_{ai}$ is taken into account through the hierarchical structure of the framework,
a potential limitation of the model is that it ignores the possible multilevel correlation between the team-specific offensive $\alpha_{jk}$ and defensive $\beta_{jk}$ coefficients, for $j=(0,1,2)$ and $k=1,\ldots,K$.
In an alternative analysis, we account for the multilevel correlation using Inverse-Wishart distributions on the covariance matrix of the team specific parameters $ \boldsymbol \Sigma_{\boldsymbol \alpha}$ and $ \boldsymbol \Sigma_{\boldsymbol \beta}$,
which are scaled in order to facilitate the specification of the priors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the predicted results from both the basic and the scaled IW model seem to replicate the observed data relatively well for most of the teams.
The total number of points scored and conceded are similar between the observed and replicated data, with the teams scoring (conceding) the most being also associated
with the highest replicated points scored (conceded) and vice versa. Relatively small discrepancies are observed between the results of the two models for some of the teams.
The total number of wins and league points are almost identical between the observed and replicated data, with the scaled IW model being associated with slightly m
ore accurate predictions compared with the basic model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following figure compares the cumulative points derived from the observed results throughout the season (the black line) and the predictions from both the basic model (in red), and the scaled Inverse-Wishart model (in blue).&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/plot_cumul_points_volley.jpg&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Posterior predictive validation of the basic (red) and IW (blue) model with respect to the observed data (black).&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For almost all teams the predicted results are relatively close to the observed data and suggest a good performance of both models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To our knowledge, this is the first modelling framework which jointly allows to predict team rankings and the outcomes of the matches during a season in volleyball.
The two alternative specifications implemented in our analysis show generally good predictive performances; between the two models, the scaled IW model seems to be
slightly more accurate compared with the basic model, but is also associated with a higher level of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>missingHE</title>
      <link>/project/missinghe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/missinghe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;missingHE&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; package, available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/missingHE/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt; which is aimed at providing some useful tools to analysts in order to handle missing outcome data under a full Bayesian framework in economic evaluations.
The package relies on the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; package &lt;code&gt;R2jags&lt;/code&gt; to implement Bayesian methods via the statistical software &lt;code&gt;JAGS&lt;/code&gt; to obtain inferences using Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods.
Different types of missing data models are implemented in the package, including selection models, pattern mixture models and hurdle models. A range of parametric distributions can be specified when modelling the typical
outcomes in an trial-based economic evaluations, namely the effectiveness and cost variabels, while simultaneously incorporating different assumptions about the missingness mechanism, which allows to easily perform
sensitvity analysis to a range of alternative missing data assumptions according to the modelling choices selected by the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;missingHE&lt;/code&gt; also provides functions, taken and adapted from other &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; packages, to assess the results of each type of model, including summaries of the posterior distributions of each model parameter,
range and imputations of the missing values, different types of model diagnostics to assess convergence of the algorithm, posterior predictive checks, model assessment measures based on the fit to the observed data,
and a general summary of the economic evaluations, including the results from probabilistic sensitivity analyses which are automatically performed within a Bayesian modelling framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the function &lt;code&gt;plot&lt;/code&gt;, when applied to the output of a model fitted using &lt;code&gt;missingHE&lt;/code&gt;, produces graphs which compare the observed and imputed values for both cost and benefit measures in each treatment group to detect possible concerns about the plausibility of the imputations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;imputed.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information, including new updates, about &amp;lsquo;missingHE&amp;rsquo; can be found at this &lt;a href=&#34;http://127.0.0.1:4321/missingHE/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dedicated page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Methods for Health Technology Assessment</title>
      <link>/project/health-economics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/health-economics/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of data used in economic evaluations typically come from a range of sources, whose evidence is combined to inform HTA decision-making. Traditionally, relative effectiveness data are derived from &lt;em&gt;randomised controlled clinical trials&lt;/em&gt; (RCTs), while healthcare resource utilisation, costs and preference-based quality of life data may come from the same study that estimated the clinical effectiveness or not. A number of HTA agencies have developed their own methodological guidelines to support the generation of the evidence required to inform their decisions. In this context, the primary role of economic evaluation for HTA is not the estimation of the quantities of interest (e.g. the computation of point or interval estimation, or hypothesis testing), but to aid decision making. The implication of this is that the standard frequentist analyses that rely on power calculations and $P$-values to estimate  statistical and clinical significance, typically used in RCTs, are not well-suited for addressing these HTA requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been argued that, to be consistent with its intended role in HTA, economic evaluation should embrace a decision-theoretic paradigm and develop ideally within a Bayesian statistical framework to inform two decisions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;whether the treatments under evaluation are cost-effective given the available evidence and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;whether the level of uncertainty surrounding the decision is acceptable (i.e. the potential benefits are worth the costs of making the wrong decision).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This corresponds to quantify the impact of the uncertainty in the evidence on the entire decision-making process (e.g. to what extent the uncertainty in the estimation of the effectiveness of a new intervention affects the decision about whether it is paid for by the public provider).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;bayesian-methods-in-hta&#34;&gt;Bayesian methods in HTA&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons that make the use of Bayesian methods in economic evaluations particularly appealing. First, Bayesian modelling is naturally embedded in the wider scheme of decision theory; by taking a probabilistic approach, based on decision rules and available information, it is possible to explicitly account for relevant sources of uncertainty in the decision process and obtain an &lt;em&gt;optimal&lt;/em&gt; course of action. Second, Bayesian methods allow extreme flexibility in modelling using computational algorithms such as &lt;em&gt;Markov Chain Monte Carlo&lt;/em&gt; (MCMC) methods; this allows to handle in a relatively easy way the generally sophisticated structure of the relationships and complexities that characterise effectiveness, quality of life and cost data. Third, through the use of prior distributions, the Bayesian approach naturally allows the incorporation of evidence from different sources in the analysis (e.g. expert opinion or multiple studies), which may improve the estimation of the quantities of interest; the process is generally referred to as evidence synthesis and finds its most common application in the use of meta-analytic tools. This may be extremely important when, as it often happens, there is only some partial (imperfect) information to identify the model parameters. In this case analysts are required to develop chain-of-evidence models. When required by the limitations in the evidence base, subjective prior distributions can be specified based on the synthesis and elicitation of expert opinion to identify the model, and their impact on the results can be assessed by presenting or combining the results across a range of plausible alternatives. Finally, under a Bayesian approach, it is straightforward to conduct &lt;em&gt;sensitivity analysis&lt;/em&gt; to properly account for the impact of uncertainty in all inputs of the decision process; this is a required component in the approval or reimbursement of a new intervention for many decision-making bodies, such as NICE in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general process of conducting a Bayesian analysis (with a view of using the results of the model to perform an economic evaluation) can be broken down in several steps, which are graphically summarized in the Figure below.&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HTA.jpg&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Process of health economic evaluation.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The starting point is the identification of the decision problem, which defines the objective of the economic evaluation (e.g. the interventions being compared, the target population, the relevant time horizon). In line with the decision problem, a statistical model is constructed to describe the (by necessity, limited) knowledge of the underlying clinical pathways. This implies, for example, the definition of suitable models to describe variability in potentially observed data (e.g. the number of patients recovering from the disease because of a given treatment), as well as the epistemic uncertainty in the population parameters (e.g.~the underlying probability that a random individual in the target population is cured, if given the treatment under study).  At this point, all the relevant data are identified, collected and quantitatively sytnthesised to derive the estimates of the input parameters of interest for the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These parameter estimates (and associated uncertainties) are then fed to the economic model, with the objective of obtaining some relevant summaries indicating the benefits and costs for each intervention under evaluation. Uncertainty analysis represents some sort of &lt;em&gt;detour&lt;/em&gt; from the straight path going from the statistical model to the decision analysis: if the output of the statistical model allowed us to know with perfect certainty the &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; value of the model parameters, then it would be possible to simply run the decision analysis and make the decision.  Of course, even if the statistical model were the &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; representation of the underlying data generating process (which it most certainly is not), because the data may be limited in terms of length of follow up, or sample size, the uncertainty in the value of the model parameters would still remain. This &lt;em&gt;parameter&lt;/em&gt; (and &lt;em&gt;structural&lt;/em&gt;) uncertainty is propagated throughout the whole process to evaluate its impact on the decision-making. In some cases, although there might be substantial uncertainty in the model inputs, this may not turn out to modify substantially the output of the decision analysis, i.e. the new treatment would be deemed as optimal irrespectively.  In other cases, however, even a small amount of uncertainty in the inputs could be associated with very serious consequences. In such circumstances, the decision-maker may conclude that the availbale evidence is not sufficient to decide on which intervention to select and require more information before a decision can be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of the above analysis can be used to inform policy makers about two related decisions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;whether the new intervention is to be considered (on average) &lt;em&gt;value for money&lt;/em&gt;, given the evidence base available at the time of decision, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;whether the consequences (in terms of net health loss) of making the wrong decision would warrant further research to reduce this &lt;em&gt;decision uncertaint&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the type and specification of the statistical and economic models vary with the nature of the underlying data (e.g. individual (ILD) level versus aggregated (ALD) data, the decision and uncertainty analyses have a more standardised set up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HTA has been slow to adopt Bayesian methods; this could be due to a reluctance to use prior opinions, unfamiliarity, mathematical complexity, lack of software, or conservatism of the healthcare establishment and, in particular, the regulatory~authorities. However, the use of Bayesian approach has been increasingly advocated as an efficient tool to integrate statistical evidence synthesis and parameter estimation with probabilistic decision analysis in an unified framework for HTA. This enables a transparent &lt;em&gt;evidence-based&lt;/em&gt; decision modelling, reflecting the uncertainty and the structural relationships in all the available~data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With respect to trial-based analyses, the flexibility and modularity of the Bayesian modelling structure are well-suited to jointly account for the typical complexities that affect ILD. In addition, prior distributions can be used as convenient means to incorporate external information into the model when the evidence from the data is limited or absent (e.g. for missing values). In the context of evidence synthesis, the Bayesian approach is particularly appealing in that it allows for all the uncertainty and correlation induced by the often heterogeneous nature of the evidence (either ALD only or both ALD and ILD) to be synthesised in a way that can be easily integrated within a decision modelling framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The availability and spread of Bayesian software among practitioners since the late 1990s, such as &lt;code&gt;OpenBUGS&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;JAGS&lt;/code&gt;, has greatly improved the applicability and reduced the computational costs of these models. Thus, analysts are provided with a powerful framework, which has been termed &lt;em&gt;comprehensive decision modelling&lt;/em&gt;, for simultaneously estimating posterior distributions for parameters based on specified prior knowledge and data evidence, and for translating this into the ultimate measures used in the decision analysis to inform cost-effectiveness conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Modelling for Health Economic Evaluations</title>
      <link>/project/bayesian-modelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/bayesian-modelling/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;modelling-framework&#34;&gt;Modelling Framework&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose a unified Bayesian framework that jointly accounts for the typical complexities of the data (e.g. correlation, skewness, spikes at the boundaries  and missingness), and that can be implemented in a relatively easy way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the usual cross-sectional bivariate outcome formed by the QALYs and total cost variables $(e_{it}, c_{it})$ calculated for the $i-$th person in group $t$ of the trial. To simplify the notation, unless necessary, we suppress the treatment indicator $t$.
We specify the joint distribution $p(e_i,c_i)$ as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
p(e_i,c_i) = p(c_i)p(e_i\mid c_i) = p(e_i)p(c_i\mid e_i)
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where, for example, $p(e_i)$ is the &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt; distribution of the QALYs and $p(c_i\mid e_i)$ is the &lt;em&gt;conditional&lt;/em&gt; distribution of the costs given the QALYs. Note that, although the two factorisations are mathematically equivalent, the choice of which to use has different practical implications. From a statistical point of view, the factorisations require the specifications of different statistical models, e.g. $p(e_i)$ or $p(e_i\mid c_i)$, which may have different approximation errors. From a clinical point of view, the two versions make different assumptions about the casual relationships between the outcomes, i.e. either $e_i$ determines $c_i$ or vice versa. We describe our analysis under the assumption that the costs are determined by the effectiveness measures and therefore we specify the joint distribution $p(e_i,c_i)$ in terms of a marginal distribution for the QALYs and a conditional distribution for the costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each individual we consider a marginal distribution $p(e_i \mid \boldsymbol \theta_e)$ indexed by a set of parameters $\boldsymbol \theta_e$ comprising a &lt;em&gt;location&lt;/em&gt; $\boldsymbol \phi_{ie}$ and a set of &lt;em&gt;ancillary&lt;/em&gt; parameters $\boldsymbol\psi_e$ typically including some measure of &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt; variance $\sigma^2_e$. We can model the location parameter using a generalised linear structure, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
g_e(\phi_{ie})= \alpha_0 \,\,[+ \ldots]
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $\alpha_0$ is the intercept and the notation $[+\ldots]$ indicates that other terms (e.g. quantifying the effect of relevant covariates) may or may not be included. In the absence of covariates or assuming that a centered version $x_i^{\star} = (x_i - \bar{x})$ is used, the parameter $\mu_e = g_e^{-1}(\alpha_0)$ represents the population average QALYs. For the costs, we consider a conditional model $p(c_i\mid e_i,\boldsymbol\theta_c)$, which explicitly depends on the QALYs, as well as on a set of quantities $\boldsymbol\theta_c$, again comprising a location $\phi_{ic}$ and ancillary parameters $\boldsymbol \psi_{c}$. For example, when normal distributions are assumed for both $p(e_i \mid \boldsymbol \theta_e)$ and $p(c_i \mid e_i, \boldsymbol \theta_c)$, i.e. bivariate normal on both outcomes, the ancillary parameters $\boldsymbol\psi_c$ include a &lt;em&gt;conditional&lt;/em&gt; variance $\tau^2_c$, which can be expressed as a function of the marginal variance $\sigma^2_c$. More specifically, the conditional variance of $p(c_i \mid e_i, \boldsymbol \theta_c)$ is a function of the marginal effectiveness and cost variances and has the closed form $\tau^2_c=\sigma^2_c - \sigma^2_e \beta^2$, where $\beta=\rho \frac{\sigma_c}{\sigma_e}$ and $\rho$ is the parameter capturing the correlation between the variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The location can be modelled as a function of the QALYs as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
g_c(\phi_{ic}) = \beta_{0} + \beta_{1}(e_{i}-\mu_{e})\,\,[+\ldots]
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, $(e_i-\mu_e)$ is the centered version of the QALYs, while $\beta_{1}$ quantifies the correlation between costs and QALYs. Assuming other covariates are either also centered or absent, $\mu_c = g_c^{-1}(\beta_{0})$ is the estimated population average cost. The Figure below shows a graphical representation of the general modelling framework.&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/framework.jpg&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Modelling framework.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The QALYs and cost distributions are represented in terms of combined &lt;em&gt;modules&lt;/em&gt;, the blue and the red boxes, in which the random quantities are linked through logical relationships. This ensures the full characterisation of the uncertainty for each variable in the model. Notably, this is general enough to be extended to any suitable distributional assumption, as well as to handle covariates in either or both the modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed framework allows jointly tackling of the different complexities that affect the data in a relatively easy way by means of its modular structure and flexible choice for the distributions of the QALYs and cost variables. Using the MenSS trial as motivating example, we start from the original analysis and expand the model using alternative specifications that progressively account for an increasing number of complexities in the outcomes. We specifically focus on appropriately modelling spikes at the boundary and missingness, as they have substantial implications in terms of inferences and, crucially, cost-effectiveness results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;example&#34;&gt;Example&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three model specifications are considered and applied to QALY data from a RCT case study: 1) Normal marginal for the QALYs and Normal conditional for the costs (which is identical to a Bivariate Normal distribution for the two outcomes); 2) Beta marginal for the QALYs and Gamma conditional for the costs; and 3) Hurdle Model. The following Figure shows the observed QALYs in both treatment groups (indicated with black crosses) as well as summaries of the posterior distributions for the imputed values, obtained from each model. Imputations are distinguished based on whether the corresponding baseline utility value is observed or missing (blue or red lines and dots, respectively) and are summarised in terms of posterior mean and $90\%$ HPD intervals.&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/imputations.jpg&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Imputed QALYs under alternative model specifications.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are clear differences in the imputed values and corresponding credible intervals between the three models in both treatment groups. Neither the Bivariate Normal nor the Beta-Gamma models  produce imputed values that capture the structural one component in the data. In addition, as to be expected, the Bivariate Normal fails to respect the natural support for the observed QALYs, with many of the imputations exceeding the unit threshold bound. These unrealistic imputed values highlight the inadequacy of the Normal distribution for the data and may lead to distorted inferences. Conversely, imputations under the Hurdle Model are more realistic, as they can replicate values in the whole range of the observed data, including the structural ones. Imputed unit QALYs with no discernible interval are only observed in the intervention group due to the original data composition, i.e. individuals associated with a unit baseline utility and missing QALYs are almost exclusively present in the intervention group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have presented a flexible Bayesian framework that can handle the typical complexities affecting outcome data in CEA, while also being relatively easy to implement using freely available Bayesian software.  This is a key advantage that can encourage practitioners to move away from likely biased methods and promote the use of our framework in routine analyses. In conclusion, the proposed framework can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jointly model costs and QALYs;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Account for skewness and structural values;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assess the robustness of the results under a set of differing missingness assumptions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original contribution of this work consists in the joint implementation of methods that account for the complexities of the data within a unique and flexible framework that is relatively easy to apply. In the next chapter we will take a step forward in the analysis and present a longitudinal model that can use all observed utility and cost data in the analysis, explore alternative nonignorable missing data assumptions, while simultaneously handling the complexities that affect the data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
