<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>publication on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/categories/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in publication on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/categories/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Some good news...</title>
      <link>/post/update-september/update-september/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-september/update-september/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the approaching of the new academic here I have received some good news for my most recently submitted paper on Bayesian parametric modelling in health economics for missing longitudinal data, which at the moment is only available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.07147&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy to announce that, after a couple of rounds of reviews, the paper has been finally accepted for publication in &lt;a href=&#34;https://rss.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/1467985X&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JSS: Series A&lt;/a&gt;. I believe that the reviewers provided a very nice feedback for improving the work and I am quite satisfied with the final version of the article which, I hope, will be of interest for anyone involved in the analsysi of partially-observed longitudinal data. I hope the pre-print of the paper will be available soon and I will &amp;ldquo;advertise&amp;rdquo; my work in two conferences in the next couple of months, where I will present the content of the paper, namely &lt;a href=&#34;https://ictmc2019.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ICTMC&lt;/a&gt; this October in Brighton, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ispor.org/conferences-education/conferences/upcoming-conferences/ispor-europe-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ISPOR Europe&lt;/a&gt; this November in Copenhagen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/vMEjhlxsBR7Fe/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really excited about this paper which represented the last part of my PhD thesis and on which I worked really hard in the last year of my studies. &lt;a href=&#34;https://agabrioblog.onrender.com/project/missing-data/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you can find a general summary of the content of the article, while &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/statistics/sites/statistics/files/presentation_priment_1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; there are some slides that describe the main idea behind the proposed model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just want to conlcude with some thanks with my co-authors of the paper, &lt;a href=&#34;http://users.stat.ufl.edu/~daniels/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/statistics/people/gianlucabaio&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ginaluca&lt;/a&gt;, without whom I would have not been able to write this paper. This was my first work with Mike, with whom I had a wonderful collaboration and I was able to visit the beatiful city of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gainesville,_Florida&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gainesville&lt;/a&gt; (FL) during my first visiting period at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ufl.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Florida&lt;/a&gt; (see thumbnail picture). I hope this will be the first of many works together in the furture!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
