<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Midia on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/categories/midia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Midia on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>`{year}`</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/categories/midia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Something old, something new, something borrowed, something blue</title>
      <link>/post/update2-february/update2-february/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update2-february/update2-february/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The moment for the second edition of the HEART&amp;rsquo;s one-day introductory course to health economics arrived at last! The course, led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=RMHUN48&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rachael Hunter&lt;/a&gt; and called &amp;ldquo;Understanding health economics in clinical trials&amp;rdquo;, took place on Tuesday 11 February and was prepared in collaboration between the HEART group and the Institute of Clinical Trials and Methodology (ICTM). I believe this second edition of the course was a success both in terms of the quality/quantity of the material covered during the six sessions throughout the day, as well as in terms of the positive feedback we received from the participants. Also, this time a new HEART member (&lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=MCCLE13&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Marie&lt;/a&gt;) joined the group and very nicely delivered the session about patient reported outcome measures (PROMs), engaging in nice discussions with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a couple of personal notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I recently attended a very interesting meeting about missing data methodology which was held by an international group of very talented senior and junior statisticians from different universities, including people like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ctu.mrc.ac.uk/about-us/senior-staff/ian-white/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ian White&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/carpenter.james&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;James Carpenter&lt;/a&gt; from UCL and the LSHTM. It was really an amazing experience to meet so many people working in different stats area but with a common passion about missing data methods (also mine!). From what I understood this series of meetings (called &amp;ldquo;MiDIA&amp;rdquo;) have been held since years but do not have a very regular schedule due to people being busy I guess, which makes totally sense. Not sure when the next one will be held but now I am definitely looking forward to the next meetings!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/kFBJt0yqZD315EFJiJ/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would also like to highlight a recent tweet from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/priment/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UCL PRIMENT CTU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Vacancy?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Vacancy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;Come join our team of health economists! &lt;br&gt;Closing date: 15 March 2020&lt;br&gt;Apply here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/IUg8JIeANX&#34;&gt;https://t.co/IUg8JIeANX&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/clinicaltrials?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#clinicaltrials&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/healtheconomics?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#healtheconomics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Priment Clinical Trials Unit (@PRIMENT_UCL) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/PRIMENT_UCL/status/1230124818244173824?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;which advertises a new position as health economist in our HEART group for performing health economics using data from clinical trials. I would encourage anyone interested in some good applied health economic work to apply for this position. Deadline 15 March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/kHZu4LDtvpY63RT1He/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To conclude, I would also like to say that I have done some updates to this website. From the inclusion of new tutorials on the use of &lt;a href=&#34;/jags/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JAGS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;/stan/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;STAN&lt;/a&gt; on different statistical topics, to a restyle of the website. In particular I had fun by playing around with some &lt;code&gt;Markdown&lt;/code&gt; code to add new features, e.g. customised alert notes and emoji that you may find on my &lt;a href=&#34;/authors/agabrio/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt;, for example. This took me so much time but I am quite satisfied with the result if I may say so. You really never stop learning new things!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
