<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publication on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/tags/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publication on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>`{year}`</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally here ...</title>
      <link>/post/update-february/update-february/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-february/update-february/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The new year is finally taking off for me and I have a couple of updates. First, I would like to remind everyone about the exciting new course &amp;ldquo;understanding health economics in clinical trials&amp;rdquo; that me and
the rest of our research team &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HEART&lt;/a&gt; have put together to support the dissemination of health economics among all people involved in the design and analysis of clinical trials.
I look forward to deliver this one-day short course together with my colleagues from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/epidemiology-health-care/research/pcph&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UCL PCPH department&lt;/a&gt; which will be structured into different sessions
during the day of Feb 11th at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/comprehensive-clinical-trials-unit/contact-us&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UCL CCTU&lt;/a&gt; - 2nd Floor, 90 High Holborn, London. The course is specifically intended for those who would like to know more
about health economics, which has become an important component in the design, analysis and most crucially, for the funding approval of clinical trials. The course will focus on the following aspects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A short intorduction to the basic concepts of health economics and why these can be relevent to different people&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A review of different types of intruments and tools used to collect health economic data in clinical trials&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A quick look at decision models with some examples&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A summary of the typical results from health economic analyses and how to interpret them&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course is still in its pilot form and therfore it is free of charge. If there are still places available, you are very welcome to join and give us your feedback!.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/RMTQiRYAuvvJb1k6al/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I am happy to announce that my recent paper about the use of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02664763.2020.1723506&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bayesian Hierarchical Models for the Prediction of Volleyball Results&lt;/a&gt; has finally
been published on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/loi/cjas20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Journal of Applied Statistics&lt;/a&gt;. I am really proud of this paper as it is my first solo paper publiched and because I have always been very invested in the general topic of
predicting sport results using probability models. To be able to publish something about this based on my own efforts is very rewarding in terms of the (small) contribution to research that I hope I was able to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/l0He0cVv8lGggpruo/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have submitted an abstract to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://euhea.eu/welcome_conference_2020.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2020 European Health Economics Association Conference&lt;/a&gt;, which this year will be held in Oslo, Norway.&lt;br /&gt;
I have now to patiently wait for the review of the abstracts and see if my work made it, either as an oral presenation or as a poster. Fingers crossed!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conferences updates and news</title>
      <link>/post/update2-october/update2-october/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update2-october/update2-october/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a quick update about some talks I gave/am about to give to advertise my research work. The one in Brighton, which I gave a couple of weeks a go at &lt;a href=&#34;https://ictmc2019.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ICTMC&lt;/a&gt;, went really well and I was glad to hear that some people were very interested in what I presented. For more info, here a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.luminpdf.com/viewer/5daad5f7ad8625001932b9a4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to my presentation about missing data methods for trial-based economic evaluations that I discussed.
Honestly, since the conference was mainly directed towards people working in clinical trials, I did not expect a huge interest in the use of Bayesian methods for economic evaluations, but apparently (and I am happy about that) I was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the chance to chat a bit with few people that I did not know, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bristol.ac.uk/social-community-medicine/people/william-hollingworth/overview.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;William Hollingworth&lt;/a&gt; from Bristol and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ndorms.ox.ac.uk/team/ines-rombach&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ines Rombach&lt;/a&gt; from Oxford, with whom I had very nice conversations about my work and other interesting topics.
I was also glad to meet some known faces, including the always lovely &lt;a href=&#34;https://cheme.bangor.ac.uk/CatrinPlumptonBiography.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Catrin Plumpton&lt;/a&gt; from Bangor University, who I met for the first time at HESG this summer and with whom I share the interest in missing data methods (even though she is a STATA and multiple imputation user, sadly).
I am also glad that I met my previous PhD secondary supervisor, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/mason.alexina&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alexina Mason&lt;/a&gt;, with whom it is always a pleasure to talk with. Unfortunately, we both missed the talk of each other becuase of time problems but it was good to catch up with her again. I am also sad that I could
not attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/leurent.baptiste&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Baptiste&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s presentation which was the last day of the conference (I had to leave the same day of my talk, the first day) and I was not also able to actually meet him. I hope we will be able to see him soon at some other conference in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/YATNr2oXRo0IE/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this past experience, I am now looking forward to meet new people at my next conference at the Bella Center in Copenhagen (thumbnail) where this year &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ispor.org/conferences-education/conferences/upcoming-conferences/ispor-europe-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ISPOR Europe 2019&lt;/a&gt; will be held. However, I believe this will be a much larger conference and therefore I will probably not have many chances to talk with people as I did at ICTMC.
Plus I am only preseting a poster this time, so it will be less likely that some people will actually notice my work, especially given the typically huge amount of presenters of this type of conferences. In the wrost case, I will enjoy Copenhagen and meet up with some old friends who live in Denmark and who will come at ISPOR to present some other work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More good news...</title>
      <link>/post/update-october/update-october/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-october/update-october/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have got two news coming up. First, the paper I wrote with Michael and Gianluca on Bayesian methdos for longitudinal data in trial-based economic evaluations has finally been published as early view on &lt;a href=&#34;https://rss.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/rssa.12522&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JRSSA&lt;/a&gt;. As I said in some earlier posts, I am super happy about this collaboration and I hope I can continue working on similar projects in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I will soon give a talk about this work at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ictmc2019.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ICTMC&lt;/a&gt; conference in Brighton, next Monday. This will be the first time at this conference and unfortunately I will only be able to remain around for one day as I need to go back to London pretty soon. I hope I will be able to enjoy my day at the conference, even though I will miss the talks of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/leurent.baptiste&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Baptiste&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/mason.alexina&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alexina&lt;/a&gt; which are scheduled for the last day of the conference. I hope I can at least have a quick chat with them the day I am around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/efDT7dqlF5N2LVHG8C/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also excited to visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brighton&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Brighton&lt;/a&gt;, since many people keep telling me that I should go and visit this sort of british version of &amp;ldquo;Rimini&amp;rdquo;. To be honest, I do not expect to find a nice wheather, given that in this period it is raining a lot in London, but I hope I will be lucky and get the only sunny day of the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have started a rubric called &lt;a href=&#34;https://agabrioblog.onrender.com/missingdata/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;missing data&lt;/a&gt; on my website, where I try to describe some of the most popular methods to handle missing data and to provide some references for anyone who could be interested in this field. I am really fascinated by statistical methods for dealing with missingness, perhaps because it was the main focus of my PhD, but I am eager to review different methods and see if I can find something really interesting. Of course, to complete this it will take more time, which I hope I will be able to find in the next months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some good news...</title>
      <link>/post/update-september/update-september/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-september/update-september/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the approaching of the new academic here I have received some good news for my most recently submitted paper on Bayesian parametric modelling in health economics for missing longitudinal data, which at the moment is only available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.07147&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy to announce that, after a couple of rounds of reviews, the paper has been finally accepted for publication in &lt;a href=&#34;https://rss.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/1467985X&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JSS: Series A&lt;/a&gt;. I believe that the reviewers provided a very nice feedback for improving the work and I am quite satisfied with the final version of the article which, I hope, will be of interest for anyone involved in the analsysi of partially-observed longitudinal data. I hope the pre-print of the paper will be available soon and I will &amp;ldquo;advertise&amp;rdquo; my work in two conferences in the next couple of months, where I will present the content of the paper, namely &lt;a href=&#34;https://ictmc2019.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ICTMC&lt;/a&gt; this October in Brighton, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ispor.org/conferences-education/conferences/upcoming-conferences/ispor-europe-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ISPOR Europe&lt;/a&gt; this November in Copenhagen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/vMEjhlxsBR7Fe/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really excited about this paper which represented the last part of my PhD thesis and on which I worked really hard in the last year of my studies. &lt;a href=&#34;https://agabrioblog.onrender.com/project/missing-data/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you can find a general summary of the content of the article, while &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/statistics/sites/statistics/files/presentation_priment_1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; there are some slides that describe the main idea behind the proposed model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just want to conlcude with some thanks with my co-authors of the paper, &lt;a href=&#34;http://users.stat.ufl.edu/~daniels/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/statistics/people/gianlucabaio&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ginaluca&lt;/a&gt;, without whom I would have not been able to write this paper. This was my first work with Mike, with whom I had a wonderful collaboration and I was able to visit the beatiful city of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gainesville,_Florida&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gainesville&lt;/a&gt; (FL) during my first visiting period at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ufl.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Florida&lt;/a&gt; (see thumbnail picture). I hope this will be the first of many works together in the furture!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
