<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/authors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Authors on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>`{year}`</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Andrea Gabrio</title>
      <link>/authors/andrea-gabrio/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/andrea-gabrio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Gabrio</title>
      <link>/authors/a-gabrio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/a-gabrio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AJ Mason</title>
      <link>/authors/aj-mason/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/aj-mason/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>G Baio</title>
      <link>/authors/g-baio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/g-baio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Hunter</title>
      <link>/authors/r-hunter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/r-hunter/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Manca</title>
      <link>/authors/a-manca/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/a-manca/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MJ Daniels</title>
      <link>/authors/mj-daniels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/mj-daniels/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/agabrio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/agabrio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am an assistant professor in Statistics in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maastrichtuniversity.nl/about-um/faculties/psychology-and-neuroscience/departments/department-methodology-and-statistics&#34;&gt;Department of methodology and statistics&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maastrichtuniversity.nl/about-um/faculties/faculty-health-medicine-and-life-sciences&#34;&gt;Faculty of Health Medicine and Life Sciences&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maastrichtuniversity.nl/&#34;&gt;Maastricht University&lt;/a&gt; in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main interests are in Bayesian statistical modelling for cost-effectiveness analysis and decision-making problems in the health systems. During my PhD I have specifically focused on the study and adoption of Bayesian methods to handle missing data in health economic evaluations and to assess the impact of their uncertainty on the output of the decision-making process. My research area involves different topics: from systematic literature reviews, case study applications, survival analysis, meta-analytic methods, multilevel models and trial-based clinical and economic analyses. Here you can find &lt;a href=&#34;/files/cv.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt; my CV&lt;/a&gt; with more details on what I have done so far and my interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am very interested in the analysis of longitudinal data, with a focus on different types of statistical methods to deal with missingness. My preferred statistical programming software and the one I am most familiar with is &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;R/RStudio&lt;/a&gt; by far, but I do also possess a good knowledge of other software such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stata-uk.com/&#34;&gt;STATA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://uk.mathworks.com/&#34;&gt;MATLAB&lt;/a&gt;. I am quite expert in the use of free open-source Bayesian software programs, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openbugs.net/w/FrontPage&#34;&gt;OpenBUGS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://mcmc-jags.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;JAGS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://mc-stan.org/&#34;&gt;STAN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have collaborated with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/statistics/research/statistics-health-economics/&#34;&gt;Statistics for Health Economic Evaluation research group&lt;/a&gt; in the Department of Statistical Science at UCL, which is mainly focused on the development and application of Bayesian methods for health economic evaluations. The group works in collaboration with academics from different institutions and its activities are aimed at providing advice to statisticians, health economists and clinicians working in economic evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also collaborated with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Health Economics Analysis and Research methodology Team&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/clinical-trials-and-methodology/&#34;&gt;Institute for Clinical Trials and Methodology&lt;/a&gt; at UCL, working primarily with the members of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/clinical-trials-and-methodology/about/priment&#34;&gt;Priment Clinical Trials Unit&lt;/a&gt;. The group focuses on the development of methodological tools for the analysis of the economic components in randomised control trials across a wide range of clinical areas and is formed by a group of interdisciplinary and varied experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading;&#34;&gt;&amp;#9818; King&#39;s note! &amp;#9818; &lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
    I am a huge fan of &lt;strong&gt;RStudio&lt;/strong&gt; and its tools, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;Rmarkdown&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt; packages, which are aimed at the construction of documents that combine text, &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; code and the output from the execution of that code: from html and pdf files to multi-page web sites and e-books (yes this website is written in &lt;strong&gt;Markdown&lt;/strong&gt;!). Oh, and I ❤ $\rm \LaTeX$.
        &lt;hr&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
