<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/authors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Authors on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Andrea Gabrio</title>
      <link>/authors/andrea-gabrio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/andrea-gabrio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Gabrio</title>
      <link>/authors/a-gabrio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/a-gabrio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Manca</title>
      <link>/authors/a-manca/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/a-manca/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AJ Mason</title>
      <link>/authors/aj-mason/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/aj-mason/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>G Baio</title>
      <link>/authors/g-baio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/g-baio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MJ Daniels</title>
      <link>/authors/mj-daniels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/mj-daniels/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Hunter</title>
      <link>/authors/r-hunter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/r-hunter/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/agabrio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/agabrio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a Research Fellow in Statistics and Health Economics in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/statistics/&#34;&gt;Department of Statistical Science&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/iehc/research/pcph&#34;&gt;Department of Primary Care and Population Health&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;University College London&lt;/a&gt; (UK). I graduated in Applied Economics from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.unipv.it/&#34;&gt;University of Pavia&lt;/a&gt; (Italy) and in Statistics and Econometrics from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.essex.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;University of Essex&lt;/a&gt; (UK). I then completed a PhD programme in Statistics at University College London, after a short visiting period in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://stat.ufl.edu/&#34;&gt;Department of Statistics&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ufl.edu/&#34;&gt;University of Florida&lt;/a&gt; (USA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main interests are in Bayesian statistical modelling for cost-effectiveness analysis and decision-making problems in the health systems. During my PhD I have specifically focused on the study and adoption of Bayesian methods to handle missing data in health economic evaluations and to assess the impact of their uncertainty on the output of the decision-making process. My research area involves different topics: from systematic literature reviews, case study applications, survival analysis, meta-analytic methods, multilevel models and trial-based clinical and economic analyses. I am very interested in the analysis of longitudinal data, with a focus on different types of statistical methods to deal with missingness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/statistics/research/statistics-health-economics/&#34;&gt;Statistics for Health Economic Evaluation research group&lt;/a&gt; in the Department of Statistical Science at UCL, which is mainly focused on the development and application of Bayesian methods for health economic evaluations. The group works in collaboration with academics from different institutions and its activities are aimed at providing advice to statisticians, health economists and clinicians working in economic evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Health Economics Analysis and Research methodology Team&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/clinical-trials-and-methodology/&#34;&gt;Institute for Clinical Trials and Methodology&lt;/a&gt; at UCL, working primarily with the members of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/clinical-trials-and-methodology/about/priment&#34;&gt;Priment Clinical Trials Unit&lt;/a&gt;. The group focuses on the development of methodological tools for the analysis of the economic components in randomised control trials across a wide range of clinical areas and is formed by a group of interdisciplinary and varied experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
