<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academic on Andrea Gabrio</title>
    <link>/tags/academic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Academic on Andrea Gabrio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/academic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>MissingHE 1.2.1</title>
      <link>/post/missinghe-121/missinghe-version121/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/missinghe-121/missinghe-version121/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have finally found some time to update the version for my R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://agabrioblog.onrender.com/missingHE/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;missingHE&lt;/a&gt;, for which version 1.2.1 is now available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/missingHE/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;.
I included two main features to the previous version of the package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I have added a new type of identifying restriction when fitting pattern mixture models through the function &amp;ldquo;pattern&amp;rdquo;. Before, only the complete case
restriction was available, which identifies the distributions of the missing data with those from the completers. Now the alternative available case restriction is can also be selected, which relies on the distributions that can be identified
among the non-completers to identify the distributions of the missing data. In this way, people can choose among at least two options for the type of restrictions and compare how this choice may affect the final estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I added a new accessory function called &amp;ldquo;ppc&amp;rdquo;, which allows to perform posterior predictive checks using the conditional parameters saved from the fitted model to generate replications of the data at each posterior iteration of the model.
The function implements a relatively large number of checks, mostly taken from the R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/bayesplot/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;bayesplot&lt;/a&gt;, which allow to assess the fit of the model to the observed data by type of outcome (effects and costs) and treatment group (control and intervention).
For example, overalyed density plots can be generated to compare the empirical and replicated densities of the data to detect possible failures of the model.&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/plotec.png&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Density plots for the observed and replicated data&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel this is very important as when fitting a Bayesian model it is crucial to assess whether the model seems to adequately capture the different characteristics of the observed data (e.g. skewness, structural values, etc.).
A wide range of predictive checks are available, including histograms (see thumbnail pciture), scatterplots, error intervals, empirical cumulative distribution fucntions, statistcis of interest and many others. In addition ,
these checks can be performed for each type of missingness model and parametric distribution chosen within missingHE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/NEvPzZ8bd1V4Y/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it is important to remember that, when dealing with missing data the fit of the model can only be checked with respect to the observed values and therefore this
check is only partial since the fit to the unibserved values can never be checked. This is also why it is not meaningful to assess the fit of a model fitted under a missing not at random assumption
because this is based on information which is not directly available from the data at hand and thus impossible to check.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discussing my thesis</title>
      <link>/post/update-interview/update-interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-interview/update-interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been kindly invited by the amazing person &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ohe.org/about-us/meet-team/chris-sampson&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Chris Sampson&lt;/a&gt; to talk about the work I inlcuded in my PhD thesis for his monthly rubric entitled  &amp;ldquo;Thesis Thursday&amp;rdquo; on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aheblog.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Academic Health Economists blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happily accepted Chris&amp;rsquo;s invitation as I beleive this initiative is really interesting and represents a nice way for newly graduated PhD students to advertise their work while also giving the chance to people interested in health economics to read about some academic work which is typically freely available to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aheblog.com/2019/09/19/thesis-thursday-andrea-gabrio/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you can find the full interview, which is not very long and resolves around 5 questions that Chris asked me about my work. I already new this blog but I have never had a proper chance to read through its posts carefully, which is a shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/13lTgtSUmqMrlu/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shall promise myself to try to check it more often from now on, using this interview as a nice motivation to do so.
In fact, there are not many blogs around health economics matters (here a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.feedspot.com/health_economics_blogs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;non-comprehensive list&lt;/a&gt;), among which The Academic Health Economists and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.statistica.it/gianluca/blog/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gianluca&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt; are my favourites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I will be able to find some time to write some nice posts about some health economic applications of my work in the next future as this is still the most interesting field for me at the moment. I am also the maintainer of another small blog called the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Health Economics Analysis and Research Methods Team (HEART) blog&lt;/a&gt;, where I occasionally write some posts on health economics together with my colleagues from the UCL department of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/epidemiology-health-care/research/pcph&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Primary Care and Population Health&lt;/a&gt;. The blog is still new but I hope it can become more active in the next months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some good news...</title>
      <link>/post/update-september/update-september/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/update-september/update-september/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the approaching of the new academic here I have received some good news for my most recently submitted paper on Bayesian parametric modelling in health economics for missing longitudinal data, which at the moment is only available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.07147&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy to announce that, after a couple of rounds of reviews, the paper has been finally accepted for publication in &lt;a href=&#34;https://rss.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/1467985X&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JSS: Series A&lt;/a&gt;. I believe that the reviewers provided a very nice feedback for improving the work and I am quite satisfied with the final version of the article which, I hope, will be of interest for anyone involved in the analsysi of partially-observed longitudinal data. I hope the pre-print of the paper will be available soon and I will &amp;ldquo;advertise&amp;rdquo; my work in two conferences in the next couple of months, where I will present the content of the paper, namely &lt;a href=&#34;https://ictmc2019.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ICTMC&lt;/a&gt; this October in Brighton, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ispor.org/conferences-education/conferences/upcoming-conferences/ispor-europe-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ISPOR Europe&lt;/a&gt; this November in Copenhagen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/vMEjhlxsBR7Fe/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really excited about this paper which represented the last part of my PhD thesis and on which I worked really hard in the last year of my studies. &lt;a href=&#34;https://agabrioblog.onrender.com/project/missing-data/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you can find a general summary of the content of the article, while &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/statistics/sites/statistics/files/presentation_priment_1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; there are some slides that describe the main idea behind the proposed model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just want to conlcude with some thanks with my co-authors of the paper, &lt;a href=&#34;http://users.stat.ufl.edu/~daniels/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/statistics/people/gianlucabaio&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ginaluca&lt;/a&gt;, without whom I would have not been able to write this paper. This was my first work with Mike, with whom I had a wonderful collaboration and I was able to visit the beatiful city of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gainesville,_Florida&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gainesville&lt;/a&gt; (FL) during my first visiting period at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ufl.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Florida&lt;/a&gt; (see thumbnail picture). I hope this will be the first of many works together in the furture!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The P value fallacy</title>
      <link>/post/p-value-fallacy/p-value-fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/p-value-fallacy/p-value-fallacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I would like to briefly comment an interesting research article written by &lt;a href=&#34;https://jhu.pure.elsevier.com/en/publications/toward-evidence-based-medical-statistics-1-the-p-value-fallacy-4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Goodman&lt;/a&gt;, who provided a clear and exemplary discussion about the typical incorrect interpretation of a standard frequentist analysis in the field of medical research. I will now briefly summarise the main argument of the paper and then add some personal comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the article describes the characteristics of the dominant school of medical statistics and highlights the logical fallacy at the heart of the typical frequentist analysis in clinical studies. This is based on a &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt; inferential approach, which starts with a given hypothesis and makes conclusions under the assumption that the hypothesis is true. This is in contrast with a &lt;em&gt;inductive&lt;/em&gt; approach, which uses the observed evidence to evaluate what hypothesis is most tenable. The two most popular methods of the frequentist paradigm are the &lt;em&gt;P value&lt;/em&gt; proposed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-1-4612-4380-9_6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fisher&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;hypothesis testing&lt;/em&gt; developed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/abs/10.1098/rsta.1933.0009?casa_token=sbSkualIaPYAAAAA%3ACxPsFTFEUK7vaxMPi5dJwUr4HoUWjrkxNh7Hl2q0owjtcU2wJHnakG-Xug7y95v1Tyqbbc8Mymaq_Q&amp;amp;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Neyman and Pearson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The P value is defined as the probability, under the assumption of no effect (null hypothesis), of obtaining a result equal to or more extreme than what was actually observed. Fisher proposed it as an informal index to be used as a measure of discrepancy between the data and the null hypothesis and therefore should not be interpreted as a formal inferential method. For example, since the P value can only be calculated on the assumption that the null hypothesis is true, it cannot be a direct measure of the probability that the null hypothesis is false. However, the main criticism to the P value is perhaps that it does not take into account the size of the observed effect, i.e. a small effect in a study with a large sample size can have the same P value as a large effect in a small study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hypothesis testing was proposed by Neyman and Pearson as an alternative approach to the P value, which assumes the existence of a null hypothesis (e.g. no effect) and an alternative hypothesis (e.g. nonzero effect). The outcome of the test is then simply to reject one hypothesis in favour of the other, solely based on the data. This exposes the researcher to two types of errors: type I error or false-positive ($\alpha$) and type II error or false-negative ($\beta$) result. Rather than focussing on single experiments, like the P value, hypothesis testing is effectively based on a deductive approach to minimise the errors over a large number of experiments. However, the price to pay to obtain this &lt;em&gt;objectivity&lt;/em&gt; is the impossibility to make any inferential statement about a single experiment. The procedure only guarantees that in the long run, i.e. after considering many experiments, we shall not often be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time a combination between the P value and hypothesis testing was developed under the assumption that the two approaches can be complementary. The idea was that the P value could be used to measure evidence in a single experiment while not violating the long run logic of hypothesis testing. The combined method is characterized by setting $\alpha$ and power $\beta$ before the experiment, then calculating a P value and rejecting the null hypothesis if the P value is less than the preset type I error rate. This means that the P value is considered a false-positive error rate specific to the data and also a measure of evidence against the null hypothesis. The &lt;strong&gt;P value fallacy&lt;/strong&gt; is born from this statement, which assumes that an event can be seen simultaneously from a long run perspective (where the observed results are put together with other results that might have occurred in hypothetical repetitions of the experiment) and from a short run perspective (where the observed results are interpreted only with respect to the single experiment). However, these views are not reconcilable since a result cannot be at the same time an interchangeable (long-run) and unique (short-run) member of a group of results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/JszzkKOlV6gTK/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally find this discussion fascinating and I believe that it is important to recognise the inconsistencies between the two alternative approaches to inference. The original authors of the two paradigms were well aware of the implications of their methods and never supported the combination of these. However, the combined approach has somehow become widely accepted in practice while its internal inconsistencies and conceptual limitations are hardly recognised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that, since the two methods are perceived as &amp;ldquo;objective&amp;rdquo;, it is generally accepted that, if combined, they can produce reliable conclusions. This, however, is not necessarily true. Accepting at face value the significance result as a binary indicator of whether or not a relation is real is dangeroues and potentially misleading. This practice wants to show that conclusions are being drawn directly from the data, without any external influence, because direct inference from data to hypothesis is thought to result in mistaken conclusions only rarely and is therefore regarded as &amp;ldquo;scientific&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This misguided approach has led to a much stronger emphasis towards the quantitative results alone (without any external input). In contrast, I believe that such perspective has the serious drawback of ignoring potentially useful information which is available (e.g. relevant medical knowledge or historical data) and which should be included in the analysis. Of course, I am aware of the potential issues that may arise from the selection and incorporation of external evidence, but I believe this should not be considered as &amp;ldquo;less reliable&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;more prone to mistakes&amp;rdquo; compared with the evidence from the available data. It is important that an agreement is reached about the selection of the type of evidence and methods to be used to perform the analysis solely based on their relevance with respect to the context analysed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HESG Summer Meeting 2019</title>
      <link>/post/hesg-norwich-2019/hesg-summer-meeting-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hesg-norwich-2019/hesg-summer-meeting-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have just come back form my first Health Economists&amp;rsquo; Study Group (&lt;a href=&#34;https://hesg.org.uk/meetings/summer-2019-university-of-east-anglia/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HESG&lt;/a&gt;) meeting, which this year was held at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uea.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of East Anglia&lt;/a&gt; in the beautiful city of Norwich,
south east of England, and where I presented some preliminary results from one of my on-going works. I have to say, it was a remarkable experience which
I really liked thanks to a wonderful and welcoming environment. I had the pleasure to talk to many people from different research areas involved in
health economics (both from academia and industry) and to see many different projects and works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I particularly enjoy the structure of the meeting, which requires some chair and discussant who have to present and discuss the paper of the authors,
who are only allowed to provide some clarification if needed. At first I thought this structure of the sessions was strange, but after attending many
sessions and experiencing this for my own paper, I feel that it is a very good way to encourage discussion about works from different people rather than
just focussing on your own presentation. Plus, the weather and always sunny, it felt like Italy for a few days.&lt;/p&gt;




  




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Norwich.jpg&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;The beautiful Norwich&amp;rsquo;s cathedral&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Other nice people and colleagues from HEART and other UCL department came to HESG with me, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=CSCLA53&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Caroline&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/comprehensive-clinical-trials-unit/meet-team/health-economics/junior-health-economist-ekaterina-kuznetsova&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ekaterina&lt;/a&gt; (aka Katia),
you can see them in thumbnail of this post. I was also pleased to meet &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/leurent.baptiste&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Baptiste&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LSHTM&lt;/a&gt;, who shares with me the interest in missing data
methods for cost-effectiveness analysis and who presented some very nice work on that. I had the chance to give some feedback to him and he did the same for me.
It felt so nice when we started discussing about some aspects of our analyses and after some minutes we simply lost track of time and everyone else disappeared.
I also had the opportunity to talk about my work with the discussant of my session, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cheme.bangor.ac.uk/CatrinPlumptonBiography.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Catrin Plumpton&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cheme.bangor.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Centre for Health Economics and Medicines Evaluation&lt;/a&gt;,
who gave me some nice feedback which I really appreciated, especially given her mathematical background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important contribution to the success of the meeting was also given by the wonderful organisation of the event, including an accommodation located very closely
to the main building of the meeting, plenty of food provided during each day, a nice bus tour of the city and a wonderful conference dinner. I must thank all the people,
who organised the event who were very extremely nice to us and who were always ready to help us for whatever need we had, with a special mention for &lt;a href=&#34;https://people.uea.ac.uk/emma_mcmanus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Emma Mcmanus&lt;/a&gt; who
was amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/cWnICjtVkJJsgGKhyX/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, everything was good. Well, almost. Going back to the works presented, as usual, the only less positive note that I would like to make
is the almost total absence of Bayesian applications. Some authors mentioned that they used some popular Bayesian program, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mrc-bsu.cam.ac.uk/software/bugs/the-bugs-project-winbugs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;WinBUGS&lt;/a&gt;, but this was
mainly related to the usual meta-analysis stuff which is pretty standardised. I hope next time I will be able to see more people going Bayesian as this is what I am.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding health economics in clinical trials</title>
      <link>/post/introduction-to-health-economics/understanding-health-economics-in-clinical-trials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/introduction-to-health-economics/understanding-health-economics-in-clinical-trials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As member of the Health Economics Analysis and Research Methods Team (&lt;a href=&#34;https://hearteam.blogspot.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HEART&lt;/a&gt;), together with my colleagues, on Tuesday 2 July I took part in a 1-day introductory short course entitled “Understanding health economics in clinical trials”, which was designed and delivered by the team. HEART is a new group of health economists who are based in UCL’s Institute of Clinical Trials and Methodology (ICTM), led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=RMHUN48&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rachael Hunter&lt;/a&gt;, and is involved at different levels in the economic components of clinical trials in different trial units at UCL. This short course was aimed at ICTM staff who are not health economists (e.g. trial managers, CIs/PIs, statisticians, data managers, research assistants, etc.) and was designed in response to the need we have identified over the last few years in working on trials as well as in response to colleagues across ICTM. This course was unique as it was intended specifically for non health economists working in trials, who wish to better understand the health economics in their study, and/or the health economist on their study. The course used a mix of lectures, group discussions and practical exercises to help participants consolidate their learning and see how to apply information from the sessions to real studies. No prior knowledge of health economics was assumed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the course was a success both in terms of the quality/quantity of the material covered during the six sessions throughout the day, as well as in terms of the positive feedback we received from the participants (almost entirely women, with the exception of two men). Many key and typically not well understood economic topics were discussed during the day, e.g. what are and how QALYs and costs are calculated, the potential limitations and issues of an economic analysis within a trial, or the role played by the protocol and analysis plan in the economic evaluation. My session was related to reporting and interpreting health economic results and I realised that most people who do not routinely deal with health economics may find difficult to grasp certain concepts or tools used in the economic analysis (e.g. what is a cost-effectiveness acceptability curve and how it can be computed). Nevertheless, I must admit that I was surprised by how many people were very motivated to learn these concepts and these &amp;ldquo;difficult&amp;rdquo; methods, often asking questions and making good comments (despite the fact that my session was the last of the course at the end of the day).&lt;br /&gt;
We ran this course as a trial as we did not have clear ideas of what an optimal design should be or the number of topics that should be covered for this type of course. We are now confident that the course has a solid structure and that there is a clear demand to learn the basic concepts of health economics, at least among people involved in trial analyses. Following the successful delivery of the course, we are planning to replicate the experience in the future, improving certain aspects of the sessions based on the feedback we received and also considering to open the course to meet the demand of a wider audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/bQrVMr3CO3QaY/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say that this was an extremely positive experience for me as it was the first time I was involved in this type of projects. Me and my colleagues worked hard to design and prepare the different sessions of the course over the last few months, find the best way to link the arguments across the sessions, provide interesting group activities and materials for the practicals, etc. I have to thank all my colleagues who contributed to the promotion and realisation of this project, with a special mention for &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=CSCLA53&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Caroline Clarke&lt;/a&gt;, who spent a lot of time and effort to organise the course and who personally contributed in giving one of the session of the course. Finally, I would also like to thank my colleague and health economist &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/comprehensive-clinical-trials-unit/meet-team/health-economics/junior-health-economist-ekaterina-kuznetsova&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ekaterina&lt;/a&gt;, with whom I had the pleasure to share the presentation and practical of my session in the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the only true negative aspect of the course was the absence of a Bayesian perspective, especially related to the interpretation of the results and the statistical methods that can be used to perform the analysis. Given the generally low familiarity of the people attending the course with statistics, I believe it was reasonable not to further confuse them with another new element into the picture. However, I truly hope that people will become more and more familiar with the importance of using tailored statistical methods in economic evaluations to avoid biased results, and from that point to justify a Bayesian approach, well, at least for me, the step is straightforward!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
